Broad Brook Company records
Connecticut Historical Society
Broad Brook Co. records
1848-1960
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Broad Brook Co.
7 linear feet and oversize items(12 boxes)
Historical Sketch
In 1842 the Phelps Manufacturing Company built a woolen mill which, after a merger, became the Broad Brook Company in 1849. The company was owned by various stockholders, with General Motors possessing the largest share of stock. The company was organized under the leadership of George Beach, Austin Dunham, Bryan E. Hooker, George Beach, Jr., Erastus Smith, and others. The Broad Brook Company manufactured wool, cotton, and other materials which were used for yarn, cloth, automobile and railroad upholstery. Beginning in January 1954 the company engaged principally in the investment business. Additionally, it owned approximately thirty five acres of unimproved real estate in Broad Brook, Hartford County, and operated a small water works system which furnished water to a portion of the town of East Windsor. In December 1953 the company sold its manufacturing operations. A week later they sold their machinery and equipment. Finally, in February 1954, the Broad Brook Company sold its manufacturing plant.
The first president of the Broad Brook Company was Homer Blanchard, who served for approximately thirty five years(1849-1884). Succeeding presidents were F.R. Cooley, Harry Brook, W.A. Fischer, and Chester Wiese. On September 23, 1959 a Plan of Reorganization was finalized between the Broad Brook Company and the State Street Investment Corporation, a Massachusetts based investment firm. All assets of the Broad Brook Company were to be transferred to the State Street Investment Corporation in exchange for shares of stock. After the shares were distributed to the Broad Brook stockholders, the company was liquidated.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of tax records, business correspondence, minutes of various meetings, financial statements, and other reports. Of the twelve boxes, three contain general ledgers of assets, liabities, and revenues. The collection also contains a picture file of the Broad Brook Company and the surrounding area. Finally, the collection contains phonograph albums of radio broadcasts.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Corporate Names
Phelps Manufacturing Co. (Broad Brook, Conn.); General Motors Corporation; State Street Investment Corporation.
Geographic Names
Connecticut -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Connecticut -- Manufactures.; Connecticut -- Industries.; East Windsor (Conn:Town)
Contents:
- I. General company records
  - Articles of Association, 1848 and Act of Incorporation, 1849 (Box 1, Folder A)
  - By-laws of the Broad Brook Co. (C. Wiese notebook); Profit and loss statements; Factory payroll statistics, 1937-1953 (Box 1, Folder B)
  - By-laws of the Broad Brook Co. notebook; Profit and loss statements (Box 1, Folder C)
  - Proxies for shareholders meetings
    - 1908-December 1909 (Box 1, Folder D)
    - 1911-February 1912 (Box 1, Folder E)
    - 1917 (Box 1, Folder F)
    - 1918 February (Box 1, Folder G)
    - 1919 (Box 1, Folder H)
  - Annuity Contracts
    - 1946-1963 (Box 1, Folder I)
    - Correspondence (IRS), 1946-1953 (Box 1, Folder J)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder K)
  - Dissolution, 1959-1960, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder L-M)
  - Renegotiation Releases (Box 1, Folder N)
  - Report of Examination of Statements, 1934-1952 Financial Statements, 1931-1954 Balance sheets and earning statements, 1925-1930. (Box 2, Folder A)
  - Broad Brook Company stockholders receipts, 1956-1959 Correspondence concerning stockholders, 1951-1960. (Box 2, Folder B)
- II. Tax Records: work sheets, correspondence, reports
  - Income tax returns, 1917-1960 (Box 3, Folder A)
  - Correspondence concerning income tax returns, 1917-1920 1922-1925. (Box 3, Folder B)
  - IRS and state correspondence concerning tax returns, 1917-1920 (Box 3, Folder C)
  - Local tax lists, 1919-1929 (Box 3, Folder D)
  - Federal income and profit tax return, 1921 (Box 3, Folder E)
  - Local tax lists "property", 1930-1941 (Box 3, Folder F)
  - Federal capital stock tax return, 1934-1940 (Box 3, Folder G)
  - State of Connecticut taxation of miscellaneous corporations, 1935. (Box 3, Folder H)
  - Treasury Department reports, 1935-1937 (Box 3, Folder I)
  - Federal capital stock tax returns, 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder J)
  - Federal income tax correspondence, 1939-1956 (Box 3, Folder K)
  - Federal income tax reports, 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder L)
  - Treasury Department formula, 1943-1950 (Box 3, Folder M)
  - Annual return of excise tax, 1943-1950 (Box 3, Folder N)
  - Tax data correspondence, 1950-1960 (Box 3, Folder O)
  - Federal income tax reports, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder P)
  - US annual information return forms 1096 & 1099
    - 1952-1956 (Box 3, Folder Q)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder R)
- III. Federal and State Income Tax Records (1909-1933)
  - Federal Income Tax Returns
    - 1909-1915 (Box 4, Folder A)
    - 1916 (Box 4, Folder B)
    - 1917 (Box 4, Folder C)
    - 1918, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder D-E)
    - 1919 (Box 4, Folder F)
  - State Income Tax Returns, 1915-1921 (Box 4, Folder G)
  - Federal Income Tax Reports, 1917-1920 (Box 4, Folder H)
  - Federal Income Tax Return and Correspondence, 1921 (Box 4, Folder I)
  - Federal Income Tax Return
    - 1922 (Tentative) (Box 4, Folder J)
    - 1922 (Amended) (Box 4, Folder K)
    - 1923 (Box 4, Folder L)
    - 1924 (Box 4, Folder M)
  - State and Federal Income Tax Return, 1924 (Box 4, Folder N)
  - Federal Income Tax Return
    - 1925 (Box 4, Folder O)
    - 1926 (Box 4, Folder P)
    - 1927 (Box 4, Folder Q)
    - 1928 (Box 5, Folder A)
    - 1929 (Box 5, Folder B)
    - 1930 (Box 5, Folder C)
    - 1931 (Box 5, Folder D)
  - Federal Income Tax Return, State Income Tax Return, and State annual report, 1932 (Box 5, Folder E)
  - Connecticut State and Federal Tax Return, New York Tax Return, and Inventory Return, 1933 (Box 5, Folder F)
- IV. Federal and State Tax Returns (1934-1960)
  - Federal Income Tax Return
    - 1934 (Box 6, Folder A)
    - 1935 (Box 6, Folder B)
    - 1936 (Box 6, Folder C)
    - 1937, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder D-E)
  - Federal Income Tax Return Correspondence, 1935-1937 (Box 6, Folder F)
  - Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder G)
  - Final Federal Income Tax Return
    - 1938, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder H-I)
    - 1939 (Box 6, Folder J)
  - Final Federal Income Tax Return, Final Federal Excess Profit Tax Return, and Final Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1940 (Box 6, Folder K)
  - Federal Income Tax Return and Federal Excess Profit Tax Return, 1941 (Box 6, Folder L)
  - Final Federal Income Tax Return, Final Federal Excess Profit Tax Return, and Final Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1942 (Box 6, Folder M)
  - Federal Income Tax Return and Federal Excess Profit Tax Return, 1943, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder N-O)
  - Tentative Federal Income Tax Return, Tentative Federal Excess Profit Tax Return, and Tentative Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1944 (Box 6, Folder P)
  - Final Federal Income Tax Return, Final Federal Excess Profit Tax Return, and Final Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1944 (Box 6, Folder Q)
  - Federal Income Tax Return and Federal Excess Profit Tax Return, 1945 (Box 6, Folder R)
  - Connecticut Income Tax Return, 194119431945 (Box 6, Folder S)
  - Federal Income Tax Return and Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1946 (Box 6, Folder T)
  - Tentative and Final Federal Income Tax Returns and Tentative and Final Connecticut Income Tax Returns, 1947 (Box 6, Folder U)
  - Federal Income Tax Return and Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1948 (Box 6, Folder V)
  - Federal Income Tax Return, Connecticut Income Tax Return, Correspondence dating to 1954 for this return, 1949, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder A-B)
  - Tentative and Final Federal Income Tax Returns and Tentative and Final Connecticut Income Tax Returns, 1950 (Box 7, Folder C)
  - Federal and Connecticut Income Tax Returns, 1951 (Box 7, Folder D)
  - Final Federal Income Tax Return, Tentative and Final Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1952 (Box 7, Folder E)
  - Federal Income Tax Return, Tentative and Final Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1953Correspondence dating up to 1954, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder F-G)
  - Tentative and Final Connecticut Income Tax Returns, 1954 (Box 7, Folder H)
  - Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1955 (Box 7, Folder I)
  - Federal Income Tax Return, 1955 (Box 7, Folder J)
  - Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1956 (Box 7, Folder K)
  - Federal Income Tax Return, 1956 (Box 7, Folder L)
  - Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1957 (Box 7, Folder M)
  - Federal Income Tax Return, 1957 (Box 7, Folder N)
  - Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1958 (Box 7, Folder O)
  - Federal Income Tax Return, 1958 (Box 7, Folder P)
  - Final Connecticut Income Tax Return, 1959 (Box 7, Folder Q)
- V. Correspondence, Reports, and Minutes
  - Director and Stockholder minutes, 1906-1909 (Box 8, Folder AA)
  - Directors meeting minutes, Stockholder meeting minutes, and resignation letters, 1919 (Box 8, Folder A)
  - Stockholders meeting notes, directors meeting notes, proxy letters, 1920 (Box 8, Folder B)
  - President's Address to the Directors, Directors meeting minutes, Stockholders meeting minutes
    - 1921 (Box 8, Folder C)
    - 1922 (Box 8, Folder D)
  - Directors meeting minutes, Stockholders meeting minutes, proxy letters
    - 1923 (Box 8, Folder E)
    - 1924 (Box 8, Folder F)
  - Reports of President and General Manager, Direcotr's meeting minutes, Stockholders meeting minutes, proxy letters, 1925 (Box 8, Folder G)
  - Directors meeting minutes, stockholders meeting minutes, proxy letters, and related material
    - 1926 (Box 8, Folder H)
    - 1927 (Box 8, Folder I)
    - 1928 (Box 8, Folder J)
    - 1929 (Box 8, Folder K)
    - 1930 (Box 8, Folder L)
  - Adjourned directors meeting minutes, 1931 (Box 8, Folder M)
  - Directors meeting minutes, proxies for annual meeting of stockholders, list of stockholders
    - 1932 (Box 8, Folder N)
    - 1933 (Box 8, Folder O)
  - Notices to Stockholders, special meeting of stockholders minutes, proxies for annual meeting of stockholders, 1934 (Box 8, Folder P)
  - Directors meeting minutes, 1934 balance sheet pertaining to 1933 corporate resolutions, 1934 resignation letters (Box 8, Folder Q)
  - Directors meeting minutes, minutes of special meetings of stockholders, corporate resolutions, proxies for special meeting of stockholders, 1935 (Box 8, Folder R)
  - Director meeting minutes, stockholder meeting minutes, corporate resolutions, proxies for special meeting of stockholders, 1936 (Box 8, Folder S)
  - Special meeting of stockholders minutes, proxies for special meetings of stockholders, minutes of special meetings of Board of Directors, 1937 (Box 8, Folder T)
  - Minutes of Directors meetings, proxies for annual meeting of stockholders, list of stockholders, 1938 (Box 8, Folder U)
- VI. Ledgers
  - General Ledger, 1935-1944 (Box 9)
  - General Ledger, 1945-1953 (Box 10)
  - War Savings Plan Accounts, 1939-1953 (Box 11)
  - Accounts Payable, 1920-1925 (Box OV)
  - Assets, liabilities, expenses, 1926-1934 (Box OV)
  - Bills payable and receivable, expenses, 1848-1863 (Box OV)
  - Bills receivable, supplies, expenses, interest, 1864-1875 (Box OV)
  - Real estate, insurance, expenses, profit and loss, 1876-1889 (Box OV)
  - Accounts payable, dye stuffs, profit and loss, 1890-1898 (Box OV)
  - Cash, fuel, wool, cloth, interest, 1899-1908 (Box OV)
  - Capital stock, wool, supplies, freight, etc., 1909-1917 (Box OV)
  - Profit and loss, capital stock, rents, oils, fuel, 1918-1920 (Box OV)
- VII. Army and Navy Awards Program
  - Photographs, certificate of award, program guide, newspaper clippings, 1942-1945 (Box 12, Folder A)
  - Broad Brook Company awards program, guest book (Box 12, Folder B)
  - Phonograph records, WTIC, 1943 February 15